<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Distributed Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/distributed/</link><description>Recent content in Distributed Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/distributed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Client-Server</title><link>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/client-server/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/client-server/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Client-Server pattern is a distributed application structure that partitions tasks or workloads between providers of a resource or service, called servers, and requesters of that resource, called clients. It fundamentally separates concerns: clients focus on user interface and request logic, while servers focus on data storage, processing, and security. This separation allows for greater scalability, maintainability, and resource sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Client-Server pattern is ubiquitous in modern computing. It&amp;rsquo;s used in web applications (browsers as clients, web servers as servers), email systems (email clients like Outlook or Thunderbird, email servers like Exchange or Gmail), database systems (applications as clients, database management systems as servers), and file sharing (clients requesting files from a file server). It&amp;rsquo;s also a core principle in microservices architectures, where individual services act as servers providing specific functionalities to client applications. Cloud computing heavily relies on this pattern, with clients accessing resources and services hosted on remote servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Browsers and Web Servers:&lt;/strong&gt; A web browser (the client) requests a webpage from a web server (like Apache or Nginx). The server processes the request, retrieves the necessary HTML, CSS, and JavaScript files, and sends them back to the browser for rendering. This is a classic example of the Client-Server pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Applications and Database Servers:&lt;/strong&gt; Applications like a customer relationship management (CRM) system (the client) interact with a database server (like MySQL, PostgreSQL, or Oracle). The CRM application sends queries to the database server to retrieve, update, or delete data. The database server handles the data management and returns the results to the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email Clients and Email Servers:&lt;/strong&gt; An email client (like Outlook or Thunderbird) connects to an email server (like Exchange or Gmail&amp;rsquo;s IMAP/SMTP servers). The client sends requests to retrieve emails, send new emails, or manage folders. The server handles the email storage, routing, and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Peer-to-Peer</title><link>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/peer-to-peer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/peer-to-peer/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Peer-to-Peer (P2P) pattern is a distributed application architecture that eliminates the need for a central server. Instead, individual nodes (peers) in the network share resources directly with each other. Each peer acts as both a client and a server, contributing its own resources (storage, bandwidth, processing power) to the network and consuming resources from other peers. This decentralization offers benefits like increased resilience, scalability, and reduced costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is particularly useful in scenarios where centralized control is undesirable or impractical, such as file sharing, content distribution, and collaborative systems. It&amp;rsquo;s also well-suited for applications that require high availability and can tolerate some level of inconsistency. P2P networks can be structured (with defined topologies) or unstructured (random connections), each offering different trade-offs in terms of efficiency and robustness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;File Sharing:&lt;/strong&gt; Applications like BitTorrent rely heavily on P2P to distribute large files efficiently. Users download pieces of a file from multiple peers simultaneously, reducing the load on any single source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cryptocurrencies:&lt;/strong&gt; Blockchain technologies, like those powering Bitcoin and Ethereum, are fundamentally P2P. Transactions are broadcast to the network and validated by multiple peers, ensuring security and transparency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decentralized Social Networks:&lt;/strong&gt; Platforms like Mastodon utilize P2P principles through federated servers (instances) that communicate with each other, allowing users to interact across different communities without a single point of control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborative Editing:&lt;/strong&gt; Some real-time collaborative editing tools use P2P to synchronize changes between users directly, reducing latency and improving responsiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BitTorrent:&lt;/strong&gt; A widely used protocol for P2P file sharing. Users download and upload file segments concurrently, creating a swarm of peers that collectively distribute the content. The tracker initially helps peers find each other, but the actual file transfer happens directly between peers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IPFS (InterPlanetary File System):&lt;/strong&gt; A P2P hypermedia protocol designed to make the web faster, safer, and more open. Content is addressed by its hash, and nodes store and serve content based on demand, creating a distributed content-addressable storage system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WebRTC:&lt;/strong&gt; A free and open-source project that provides real-time communication capabilities directly between browsers and mobile applications. It uses P2P connections for audio and video streaming, eliminating the need for a dedicated signaling server for media transfer (though signaling is still required for connection setup).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>