<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Reliability Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/reliability/</link><description>Recent content in Reliability Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 18:35:12 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/reliability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Load Shedding</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/load_shedding/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 18:35:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/load_shedding/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Load shedding is a mechanism for gracefully handling overload situations in a system. When demand exceeds available resources (CPU, memory, network, database connections, etc.), a load shedding strategy is employed to selectively reject or delay requests, preventing the system from complete failure. It prioritizes critical functionality over non-essential features, ensuring core services remain operational even under stress. Rather than crashing or becoming unresponsive, the system actively manages the load by temporarily sacrificing less important operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is crucial for building resilient systems that can withstand unexpected traffic spikes or resource constraints. Effective load shedding involves identifying critical and non-critical services, implementing thresholds for resource usage, and defining a clear policy for dropping or delaying requests. The goal is to maintain a reasonable level of service for the most important functions, even if it means temporarily degrading or denying access to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Load shedding is used in a variety of scenarios, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sudden Traffic Spikes:&lt;/strong&gt; E-commerce websites during flash sales, online gaming platforms during popular events, or news sites during breaking news.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downstream Service Outages:&lt;/strong&gt; When a dependency becomes unavailable, preventing a cascading failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource Exhaustion:&lt;/strong&gt; When CPU, memory, or database connections are at their limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preventing Denial-of-Service (DoS) Attacks:&lt;/strong&gt; Briefly rejecting requests to mitigate the impact of malicious traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintaining User Experience:&lt;/strong&gt; Prioritizing requests that impact user-facing responsiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix employs sophisticated load shedding techniques to handle massive user traffic. When their systems are under heavy load, they might temporarily reduce the quality of video streams for some users, delay non-critical updates to their recommendation engine, or return a &amp;ldquo;try again later&amp;rdquo; message for less important features. This ensures that the core streaming functionality remains available to the majority of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS Auto Scaling Groups with Termination Policies:&lt;/strong&gt; AWS Auto Scaling Groups allow you to automatically adjust the number of EC2 instances based on demand. However, when scaling down (reducing instances) due to cost or reduced load, a &lt;em&gt;termination policy&lt;/em&gt; determines which instances are removed. Common policies include &lt;code&gt;OldestLaunchTemplate&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;OldestInstance&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;Default&lt;/code&gt;. These policies act as a form of load shedding; the service sheds load by removing less &amp;ldquo;important&amp;rdquo; (e.g., older) instances to maintain capacity for the most critical requests. The selection of which instance to terminate directly affects which load gets shed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redis Maxmemory Policy&lt;/strong&gt;: Redis allows you to configure a maximum memory usage (&lt;code&gt;maxmemory&lt;/code&gt;). When Redis reaches this limit, it applies a configured &lt;em&gt;eviction policy&lt;/em&gt; (e.g., &lt;code&gt;volatile-lru&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;allkeys-lru&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;random-approx-srcmapcount&lt;/code&gt;). These policies determine which keys are removed to free up memory and prevent Redis from crashing. Removing keys is a form of load shedding, forfeiting access to invalidated data to maintain server availability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Outbox Pattern</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/outbox_pattern/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 18:22:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/outbox_pattern/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Outbox Pattern addresses the challenge of reliably publishing events in a transactional context. When an application modifies its data and needs to publish an event to notify other services, ensuring both operations occur atomically is crucial. Directly publishing events from the application can lead to eventual consistency issues if publishing fails after the database transaction succeeds, or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern solves this by introducing an &amp;ldquo;Outbox&amp;rdquo; – a table within the application’s database where all events intended for external systems are first persisted as data. A separate process, typically a reliable message broker or a background worker, then polls this Outbox table and publishes the events. Because event persistence happens &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the same database transaction as the data changes, atomicity is guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Outbox Pattern is commonly used in microservice architectures to provide reliable event-driven communication. Specifically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eventual Consistency:&lt;/strong&gt; When strong consistency across services isn’t strictly required, yet reliable notification is essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Transactions:&lt;/strong&gt; As a replacement for complex and often problematic distributed transactions (two-phase commit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoupling:&lt;/strong&gt; Decoupling the application logic from the specifics of the message broker. The application only needs to write to a database table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reliable Messaging:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring that events are not lost even in the face of temporary network outages or message broker unavailability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka with Debezium:&lt;/strong&gt; Debezium is a change data capture (CDC) platform that integrates with databases like PostgreSQL, MySQL and others. It monitors database changes, including insertions into an Outbox table, and streams those changes as Kafka events. This lets applications publish events by simply writing to the Outbox without needing to directly interact with Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Cloud Stream with JDBC Outbox:&lt;/strong&gt; Spring Cloud Stream provides a framework for building event-driven microservices. Combined with a JDBC Outbox implementation, it allows applications to persist events in a relational database. A binder component then periodically polls the Outbox table and publishes the events to a configured message broker (e.g., RabbitMQ, Kafka). This simplifies event publishing and ensures transactional consistency within the Spring application context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rails Event Store:&lt;/strong&gt; A Ruby gem that provides an event store implementation, often utilizing an Outbox table in the application&amp;rsquo;s database. Rails applications can then persist events to this Outbox as part of their database transactions, and a separate process handles publishing those events to downstream systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Transactional Consumer</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/transactional_consumer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:52:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/transactional_consumer/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Transactional Consumer pattern ensures that messages received from a message broker are processed reliably and atomically. It handles message consumption within a database transaction, allowing for either complete processing of a message batch or a full rollback in case of failure. This prevents partial updates and ensures data consistency. The pattern relies on the broker&amp;rsquo;s ability to acknowledge messages at a batch level and negatively acknowledge individual messages, allowing for redelivery of failed messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is especially useful in scenarios where message processing involves writing to multiple tables or performing complex operations that must be either entirely successful or entirely undone. It is critical for maintaining data integrity in distributed systems where failures are expected. It enables &amp;ldquo;exactly-once&amp;rdquo; processing semantics (or at least a very strong approximation) despite the inherent &amp;ldquo;at-least-once&amp;rdquo; delivery guarantees of most message brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Transactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Applying debits and credits across multiple accounts. A failure in applying one part of the transaction must roll back all changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order Processing:&lt;/strong&gt; Updating inventory, creating shipping labels, and charging the customer. An incomplete order due to a system failure needs rollback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event Sourcing:&lt;/strong&gt; When reapplying a stream of events to rebuild state, ensuring all events are processed or none are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Pipelines:&lt;/strong&gt; Processing a batch of data records where intermediate states are not consistent until the whole batch is applied.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka with Debezium &amp;amp; Spring:&lt;/strong&gt; Debezium captures database changes as Kafka events. A Spring application consuming these events can use the &lt;code&gt;KafkaTransactionManager&lt;/code&gt; within a &lt;code&gt;@Transactional&lt;/code&gt; method. If any database operation within the method fails, Spring automatically rolls back the transaction and Debezium, in conjunction with Kafka&amp;rsquo;s configuration (e.g., &lt;code&gt;acks=all&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;enable.idempotence=true&lt;/code&gt;), ensures the message is retried.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RabbitMQ with pika and SQLAlchemy:&lt;/strong&gt; Using the &lt;code&gt;pika&lt;/code&gt; Python library to consume messages from RabbitMQ and &lt;code&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/code&gt; to interact with a database. You would begin a SQLAlchemy transaction, process each message, and commit or rollback the transaction based on success or failure. The consumer would negatively acknowledge any messages that cause a rollback to allow for redelivery. Idempotency should be considered within the message processing logic for ultimate safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS SQS with DynamoDB &amp;amp; AWS Lambda:&lt;/strong&gt; An AWS Lambda function triggered by messages in SQS can use DynamoDB Transactions to process messages atomically. The Lambda function would read a batch of messages, initiate a DynamoDB transaction, process each message’s data, and then commit or rollback the transaction. SQS&amp;rsquo;s visibility timeout and dead-letter queue features provide the necessary mechanisms for handling failures and redelivering messages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Transactional Outbox</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/transactional_outbox/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:32:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/transactional_outbox/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Transactional Outbox pattern solves the problem of reliably publishing events in a microservices architecture when an event needs to be triggered as a direct result of a database transaction. It ensures that events are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; published if the transaction fails, maintaining data consistency. Instead of directly publishing events from the application code, the pattern introduces an &amp;ldquo;outbox&amp;rdquo; table within the same database transaction as the core business logic. A separate process then asynchronously reads and publishes events from this outbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is crucial in scenarios involving eventual consistency between services. When data changes in one service, it needs to notify other interested services without risking data loss or duplication. Direct publishing can lead to inconsistency if the publish operation fails &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the database commit. The Transactional Outbox avoids this by guaranteeing that event publication is tied to the success of the database transaction, offering a ‘least once’ delivery guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Transactional Outbox is broadly used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; Coordinating data changes and events between multiple independently deployable services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event-Driven Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Situations where business processes rely on asynchronous, reactive communication through events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Transactions (Saga Pattern):&lt;/strong&gt; As a reliable way to publish events that drive the Saga execution, ensuring atomicity across services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order Processing Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; When an order is created, updated, or cancelled, multiple events (e.g., &lt;code&gt;OrderCreated&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;OrderShipped&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;OrderCancelled&lt;/code&gt;) need to be reliably published to inventory, shipping, and billing services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debezium:&lt;/strong&gt; Debezium is a distributed platform for change data capture (CDC). It monitors database tables for changes and publishes those changes as events. Internally, Debezium often leverages a transactional outbox pattern (specifically the log-based CDC approach paired with outbox tables) to &lt;em&gt;reliably&lt;/em&gt; capture changes from the database without missing updates, even during database failures. It reads the outbox to know which events need to be delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Cloud Stream with Kafka:&lt;/strong&gt; Spring Cloud Stream simplifies the development of event-driven microservices using technologies like Apache Kafka. When used together, an application can insert messages into an outbox table within its database transaction. A separate binder component (provided by Spring Cloud Stream) polls this outbox table and reliably publishes the messages to Kafka, ensuring the event is only sent if the database transaction has been successfully committed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Axon Framework:&lt;/strong&gt; Axon Framework is a framework for building event-driven microservices in Java. It provides built-in support for the Transactional Outbox pattern, enabling developers to easily publish events as part of their database transactions. Axon manages the outbox table and the event publishing process, abstracting away much of the complexity of implementing the pattern manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Shadow Deployment</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/shadow_deployment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/shadow_deployment/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Shadow Deployment is a technique to test changes in a live production environment without impacting real users. It involves duplicating real production traffic to a new, &amp;ldquo;shadow&amp;rdquo; version of the application. This allows for observing the new system&amp;rsquo;s behavior under realistic load, identifying potential issues like performance bottlenecks, errors, or unexpected side effects, before a full rollout. The shadow system doesn’t serve responses to users; it purely receives and processes requests for monitoring purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern mitigates risks associated with deploying untested code and is a crucial component of robust continuous delivery pipelines. It allows teams to gain confidence in new features, bug fixes, or infrastructure changes under production conditions. Post-deployment analysis of shadow traffic can also yield valuable insights into user behavior and system interactions, informing further optimizations and refinements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Feature Validation:&lt;/strong&gt; Testing the functionality and performance of a new feature with live traffic without exposing it to end-users. This is vital for complex features that are difficult to test comprehensively in staging environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Evaluating the performance characteristics of a new application version under actual load conditions, detecting regressions or performance improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Schema Migrations:&lt;/strong&gt; Verifying the impact of database schema changes by running them against a shadow database populated with mirrored production data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrastructure Changes:&lt;/strong&gt; Validating changes to infrastructure components like caching layers, message queues, or load balancers without user disruption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canary Release Preparation:&lt;/strong&gt; As a precursor to canary releases, shadow deployment provides a first line of defense, identifying critical issues before even a small subset of users are exposed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix extensively uses shadow deployment, particularly for components of their recommendation engine and billing system. They mirror production traffic to shadow instances to evaluate new ranking algorithms or billing logic without affecting user experience. Any discrepancies are flagged and investigated before a full rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn:&lt;/strong&gt; LinkedIn employs shadow deployment to test changes to their core serving infrastructure. By shadowing production requests against new code paths, they can assess the impact on latency, throughput, and error rates before serving the changes to real users. This allows them to maintain a high level of service reliability during frequent deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istio (Service Mesh):&lt;/strong&gt; Istio, a popular service mesh, offers built-in support for traffic shadowing. You can configure it to mirror a percentage of traffic to a shadow version of a service, enabling testing and validation in a production setting. Traffic mirroring rules can be precisely controlled using Istio&amp;rsquo;s configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Canary Release</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/canary_release/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/canary_release/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Canary Release pattern is a deployment strategy where a new version of software is rolled out to a small subset of users or servers before being made available to the entire infrastructure. This allows for real-world testing of the new version with minimal impact, enabling teams to detect and address any unforeseen issues, performance regressions, or bugs in a controlled manner. The &amp;ldquo;canary&amp;rdquo; acts as an early warning system, hence the name, alerting the team to potential problems before a wider deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern prioritizes risk reduction and user experience. By observing the canary in production, teams can validate key metrics, gather user feedback, and ensure the stability of the new release. If the canary performs as expected, the rollout can proceed to more users; if issues arise, the new version can be quickly rolled back, preventing a widespread outage or negative impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architecture:&lt;/strong&gt; Canary releases are exceptionally well-suited for microservices. New versions of individual services can be deployed to a small number of instances behind a load balancer, allowing for targeted testing and minimal disruption to other services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-Traffic Websites &amp;amp; Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Rolling out updates to a small percentage of users during peak hours allows for observation of performance under realistic load without affecting the majority of the user base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex System Updates:&lt;/strong&gt; When updates involve significant changes to core functionality or dependencies, a canary release provides a safety net to ensure compatibility and stability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A/B Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Can be used in conjunction with A/B testing. A new version can be the &amp;ldquo;B&amp;rdquo; variant tested against a current version (&amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo;) allowing business metrics to drive the percentage rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gmail:&lt;/strong&gt; Gmail frequently employs canary releases to test new features. A small percentage of Gmail users (often Google employees) may see a new interface or functionality before it&amp;rsquo;s released to the general public. Monitoring these &amp;ldquo;canary&amp;rdquo; users’ behavior and reporting any issues helps refine the feature before a broad rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS CodeDeploy:&lt;/strong&gt; AWS CodeDeploy supports canary deployments for applications running on EC2, ECS, and other AWS services. It allows configuring incremental deployment strategies, automatically shifting traffic to the new version while monitoring its health. If problems are detected, CodeDeploy can automatically halt the deployment or roll back to the previous version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker Swarm/Kubernetes:&lt;/strong&gt; Container orchestration platforms like Docker Swarm and Kubernetes have built-in support for rolling updates and, by extension, canary deployments. You can specify the number of replicas for a new version and gradually increase them while monitoring performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LaunchDarkly:&lt;/strong&gt; As a Feature Management platform, LaunchDarkly specifically facilitates canary releases (and many other deployment strategies) by allowing development teams to release features to specific users or percentage of traffic, monitor performance, and rollback instantly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Geo-Replication</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/geo-replication/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:33:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/geo-replication/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Geo-Replication is a technique used to distribute data across multiple geographically diverse locations. This is done to improve performance for users in those regions (by reducing latency), increase availability and fault tolerance (by having backups in different locations), and provide disaster recovery capabilities. The core idea involves copying data between databases or storage systems situated in different geographical areas, ensuring that if one location experiences an outage, others can continue to serve requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern typically leverages asynchronous replication to minimize impact on primary database operations. Data is written to a primary region and then propagated to secondary regions. Different consistency models can be employed – from eventual consistency to stronger forms like read-after-write consistency – depending on the application’s needs. Geo-replication is essential for globally distributed applications that require high uptime and responsive user experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geo-Replication is widely used in scenarios requiring:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low Latency:&lt;/strong&gt; Serving content closer to users drastically reduces response times. Content Delivery Networks (CDNs) are a prime example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Availability:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring continued service even if one region becomes unavailable due to natural disasters, network outages, or other failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disaster Recovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Providing a readily available backup of data in a separate geographical location for quick recovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read Scalability:&lt;/strong&gt; Offloading read traffic to geographically distributed replicas, lessening the load on the primary database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compliance:&lt;/strong&gt; Meeting data residency requirements by storing data within specific geographical boundaries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon DynamoDB Global Tables:&lt;/strong&gt; DynamoDB Global Tables automatically and continuously replicate data across AWS regions. Applications can then read and write data in any region, and DynamoDB handles the replication process, providing low-latency access and high availability. This allows globally distributed applications to operate seamlessly, mitigating regional outages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Spanner:&lt;/strong&gt; Spanner is a globally distributed, scalable, and strongly consistent database service. It uses TrueTime, a highly accurate time synchronization system, to ensure consistent replication across multiple data centers and geographical locations. This allows users to read and write to the nearest replica, benefitting from low latency and high availability with guarantees of transactional consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CockroachDB:&lt;/strong&gt; CockroachDB is a distributed SQL database designed for resilience and scalability. It automatically replicates data across zones and regions, ensuring fault tolerance and low latency. CockroachDB uses a Raft consensus algorithm to manage distributed data and guarantees strong consistency even in the face of failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cluster-based Architecture</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/cluster-based_architecture/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/cluster-based_architecture/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;A Cluster-based Architecture involves grouping multiple interconnected computers (nodes) together to work as a single system. This approach enhances performance, availability, and scalability by distributing workloads across the cluster. The nodes typically share resources and are managed by software that coordinates their activities, presenting a unified interface to users or other systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is commonly used in scenarios demanding high throughput, low latency, and continuous availability. It&amp;rsquo;s essential for handling large volumes of data, serving numerous concurrent users, and ensuring resilience against hardware failures. Applications like web servers, databases, and big data processing systems frequently employ cluster-based architectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Distributing web server load across multiple instances to handle peak traffic and ensure responsiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating database replicas and distributing queries to improve read performance and provide failover capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Data Processing:&lt;/strong&gt; Parallelizing data processing tasks across a cluster of machines using frameworks like Hadoop or Spark.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Computing:&lt;/strong&gt; The foundation of most cloud services, allowing for on-demand resource allocation and scalability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaming Servers:&lt;/strong&gt; Hosting game worlds and handling player interactions across multiple servers to support a large player base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes:&lt;/strong&gt; A container orchestration platform that automates the deployment, scaling, and management of containerized applications across a cluster of nodes. It provides features like self-healing, load balancing, and automated rollouts/rollbacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apache Cassandra:&lt;/strong&gt; A highly scalable, distributed NoSQL database designed to handle large amounts of data across many commodity servers, providing high availability with no single point of failure. Data is replicated across multiple nodes in the cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Web Services (AWS):&lt;/strong&gt; Many AWS services, such as Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2) and Relational Database Service (RDS), are built on cluster-based architectures to provide scalability and reliability. Auto Scaling groups automatically adjust the number of EC2 instances in a cluster based on demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Kubernetes Engine (GKE):&lt;/strong&gt; Google&amp;rsquo;s managed Kubernetes service, providing a fully-featured, production-ready environment for deploying and managing containerized applications on a cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Replication</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/replication/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/replication/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Replication pattern addresses the need for data consistency and availability across multiple systems. It involves creating and maintaining multiple copies of data, ensuring that if one copy fails, others are available to serve requests. This enhances fault tolerance, improves read performance by distributing load, and enables geographic distribution of data for lower latency access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replication is a cornerstone of modern data management, primarily utilized in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Databases:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring data durability and high availability through master-slave or multi-master setups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content Delivery Networks (CDNs):&lt;/strong&gt; Caching static content closer to users for fast load times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed File Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Like Hadoop&amp;rsquo;s HDFS or cloud storage solutions, replicating files across multiple nodes for reliability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Message Queues:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintaining multiple copies of messages to prevent loss during broker failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blockchain Technology:&lt;/strong&gt; Distributing the ledger across a network of nodes to ensure immutability and transparency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon S3:&lt;/strong&gt; Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Simple Storage Service replicates data across multiple Availability Zones within a region. This ensures that even if one AZ experiences an outage, data remains accessible from other AZs. S3 also offers cross-region replication for disaster recovery and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka:&lt;/strong&gt; Kafka uses replication to maintain multiple copies of topics and partitions across brokers in a cluster. The replication factor determines how many copies exist. This ensures that if a broker fails, the data is still available from the other replicas, providing high fault tolerance and data durability for streaming applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PostgreSQL:&lt;/strong&gt; PostgreSQL supports various replication methods, including streaming replication and logical replication. Streaming replication creates physical copies of the database, ensuring high performance and data consistency. Logical replication allows for the replication of specific data changes, providing more granular control and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Two-Phase Commit</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/two-phase_commit/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/two-phase_commit/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Two-Phase Commit (2PC) protocol is a distributed algorithm used to ensure atomic commits across multiple transaction participants. In essence, it guarantees that either &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; participants commit changes to the database or &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; do, maintaining data consistency in a distributed environment. This is crucially important when a single logical operation necessitates updates to multiple independent systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process involves a coordinator and multiple resource managers. The coordinator initiates the commit attempt, and the resource managers execute the tentative changes. The first phase (prepare) checks if all participants &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; commit. The second phase (commit or rollback) applies the changes if all voted to commit, or reverts them if any voted to abort. While reliable, 2PC can introduce blocking and performance issues, making it less suitable for high-throughput or loosely-coupled systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-Phase Commit is frequently employed in scenarios where transactional integrity is paramount across multiple data sources. Common use cases include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Databases:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintaining consistency when a transaction modifies data in several databases across a network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices with Eventual Consistency Requirements:&lt;/strong&gt; Though often avoided in favor of Sagas due to its blocking nature, 2PC can be used where strict consistency is needed between two interacting microservices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Message Queues and Transactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring that a message is both sent to a queue and a corresponding database update is completed atomically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XA Transactions:&lt;/strong&gt; A standard for distributed transaction processing, relying heavily on 2PC.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM CICS:&lt;/strong&gt; IBM’s Customer Information Control System (CICS) resource manager often utilizes 2PC to coordinate transactions that span multiple CICS regions and database systems. When a CICS transaction requires updates to both a local database and a remote CICS region’s database, 2PC ensures atomicity. CICS acts as both a coordinator and a participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JTA (Java Transaction API):&lt;/strong&gt; This Java API provides a standardized way to manage transactions across multiple resources, like databases and message queues. It frequently uses 2PC behind the scenes (through XA support) ensuring that all involved resources either commit or rollback the transaction together. Application servers like GlassFish or WildFly use JTA for transaction management using 2PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Sharding:&lt;/strong&gt; When data is sharded across multiple database instances, 2PC can be applied to ensure that updates related to a single logical entity become visible consistently across all shards. This is often implemented in custom sharding solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>