<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Infrastructure Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/infrastructure/</link><description>Recent content in Infrastructure Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:16:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/infrastructure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reverse Proxy</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/reverse_proxy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:16:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/reverse_proxy/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Reverse Proxy pattern involves a server that sits in front of one or more backend servers and intercepts client requests. Instead of clients connecting directly to backend servers, they connect to the reverse proxy, which then forwards the requests to the appropriate backend server. The reverse proxy then receives responses from the backend and returns them to the client as if it originated from the proxy itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern offers numerous benefits, including improved security, load balancing, scalability, and simplified administration. By hiding the complexities and specific configurations of the backend servers, the reverse proxy presents a unified interface to the outside world, enhancing the overall system architecture and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reverse proxies are widely used in modern web architectures for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Load Balancing:&lt;/strong&gt; Distributing client requests across multiple backend servers to prevent overload and improve responsiveness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security:&lt;/strong&gt; Protecting backend servers from direct exposure to the internet, mitigating DDoS attacks, and providing SSL encryption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caching:&lt;/strong&gt; Storing frequently accessed content closer to the client, reducing latency and server load.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSL Termination:&lt;/strong&gt; Offloading SSL encryption/decryption from backend servers, freeing up resources for application logic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;URL Rewriting:&lt;/strong&gt; Simplifying complex URLs or masking internal server structures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A/B Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Routing traffic to different versions of an application for testing purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NGINX:&lt;/strong&gt; A popular open-source web server and reverse proxy, often used to handle static content, load balance traffic, and provide SSL termination for web applications. Many high-traffic websites rely on NGINX as a reverse proxy to ensure performance and availability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HAProxy:&lt;/strong&gt; Another widely used open-source load balancer and reverse proxy, known for its high performance and reliability. It&amp;rsquo;s commonly deployed in front of database servers, application servers, and other network services to distribute traffic and improve resilience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon CloudFront:&lt;/strong&gt; Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Content Delivery Network (CDN) service acts as a reverse proxy, caching content at edge locations around the world to deliver faster and more reliable experiences to users. It also provides security features like DDoS protection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Varnish Cache:&lt;/strong&gt; A powerful HTTP accelerator (reverse proxy) designed for caching content. It&amp;rsquo;s frequently used in front of web servers like Apache or Nginx to dramatically improve response times and reduce server load.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Service Mesh</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/service_mesh/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:12:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/service_mesh/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;A service mesh is a dedicated infrastructure layer for facilitating service-to-service communication within a microservices application. It manages concerns like service discovery, load balancing, encryption, observability, and traffic management, abstracting these complexities away from individual service code. The core of a service mesh typically consists of a network of lightweight proxy instances (often referred to as &amp;ldquo;sidecars&amp;rdquo;) deployed alongside each service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Service meshes are crucial in complex, distributed systems where managing inter-service communication manually becomes unsustainable. They enable developers to focus on business logic, while the mesh handles the operational challenges of a dynamic microservice architecture. They provide a comprehensive solution for ensuring reliability, security, and observability in cloud-native applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; The most common use case, enabling reliable communication, resilience, and observability across numerous services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-Native Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Facilitates the adoption of cloud-native principles like containerization and dynamic scaling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex Deployments:&lt;/strong&gt; Managing communication and security in multi-cluster, multi-region deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zero-Trust Security:&lt;/strong&gt; Enforcing mutual TLS authentication and access control policies between services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canary Releases &amp;amp; A/B Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Implementing advanced traffic management strategies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istio:&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps the most well-known service mesh, Istio provides traffic management, observability, and security for microservices. It leverages Envoy as its proxy and offers features like traffic shifting, fault injection, and detailed metrics collection. Istio is often used in Kubernetes environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linkerd:&lt;/strong&gt; A lightweight and performant service mesh designed for simplicity and ease of operation. Linkerd also uses a proxy (sadly, no longer Envoy) and focuses on providing core functionality like automatic retries, circuit breaking, and TLS encryption, with a strong emphasis on observability. Linkerd is often chosen for its lower resource footprint and easier learning curve than more complex meshes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS App Mesh:&lt;/strong&gt; A fully managed service mesh from Amazon Web Services, integrated with other AWS services like ECS, EKS, and Lambda. It uses Envoy as its proxy and provides similar features to Istio and Linkerd, but with the benefits of AWS&amp;rsquo;s managed infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Config Server</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/config_server/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:37:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/config_server/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Config Server pattern centralizes configuration management for distributed systems, particularly microservices. Instead of embedding configuration directly within applications or duplicating it across various deployment environments, a dedicated Config Server acts as a single source of truth. Client applications retrieve their configurations from the server dynamically, allowing changes to be propagated without requiring application restarts or redeployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern greatly simplifies configuration management, improves consistency, and enables dynamic updates in response to changing conditions. It supports differing configurations for different environments (development, staging, production) and application instances, bolstering agility and reducing operational overhead. The Config Server often integrates with version control systems for auditability and rollback capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Config Server pattern is widely used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; As configurations are often environment-specific and need to be updated frequently, a config server is essential for managing disparate service settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-Native Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Dynamic environments and autoscaling necessitate the ability to adjust configurations on the fly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Integration/Continuous Delivery (CI/CD) Pipelines:&lt;/strong&gt; Allows settings to be updated as part of automated deployments without altering the application code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large-Scale Distributed Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Simplifies control and auditability of application settings across a complex infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Cloud Config:&lt;/strong&gt; A popular Java-based framework that provides a Config Server implementation coupled with Spring Cloud’s service discovery capabilities. It supports various backends like Git, Vault, and a database, enabling flexible configuration storage and versioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azure App Configuration:&lt;/strong&gt; Microsoft Azure&amp;rsquo;s fully managed configuration service. It provides dynamic configuration updates, feature flags, and secret management, integrating seamlessly with other Azure services. Features include versioning, labels, and access control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consul (HashiCorp):&lt;/strong&gt; While also a service discovery tool, Consul includes a key-value store that effectively functions as a distributed configuration server. Applications can subscribe to configuration updates and receive notifications when changes occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>