<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cross-Cutting Concerns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/cross-cutting/</link><description>Recent content in Cross-Cutting Concerns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/cross-cutting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Externalized Configuration</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/externalized_configuration/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/externalized_configuration/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Externalized Configuration pattern separates application configuration data from the application&amp;rsquo;s code. Instead of hardcoding configuration values within the code, these values are stored in external sources like configuration files, databases, environment variables, or dedicated configuration servers. This decoupling allows for easy modification of application behavior without requiring code changes, redeployments, or restarts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern enhances maintainability, portability, and security. It enables different configurations for different environments (development, testing, production) easily, simplifies configuration management for operations teams, and minimizes the risk of exposing sensitive information directly within the codebase. It is a foundational best practice for modern software development and deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environment-Specific Settings:&lt;/strong&gt; Different environments (development, staging, production) often require varying database connection strings, API keys, and feature flags. Externalized configuration makes it easy to manage these differences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamic Updates:&lt;/strong&gt; When application parameters need to be changed frequently (e.g., retry intervals, logging levels), externalizing them allows modification without redeployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuration as Code:&lt;/strong&gt; Managing configuration in version control systems alongside code provides an audit trail and facilitates rollbacks. Tools like Kubernetes ConfigMaps and Secrets leverage this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; In distributed systems, externalized configuration is critical for managing the settings of each microservice independently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compliance and Security:&lt;/strong&gt; Storing sensitive information like passwords and API keys outside the code base is essential for compliance and security best practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Cloud Config (Java/Spring):&lt;/strong&gt; Spring Cloud Config provides a framework for managing application properties externally, through files stored in version control systems (like Git) or via a central configuration server. Microservices can connect to this server to retrieve their configuration details dynamically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.env Files (Python/Node.js/Ruby):&lt;/strong&gt; The widespread practice of using &lt;code&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt; files to store environment variables is a simple form of externalized configuration. Libraries like &lt;code&gt;python-dotenv&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;dotenv&lt;/code&gt; in Node.js load these variables into the application&amp;rsquo;s environment during runtime.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes ConfigMaps and Secrets:&lt;/strong&gt; Kubernetes provides ConfigMaps and Secrets to store configuration data. ConfigMaps are suited for non-sensitive data, while Secrets are designed for sensitive information like passwords. Pods can mount these resources as files or expose them as environment variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azure App Configuration/AWS AppConfig:&lt;/strong&gt; These cloud services allow managing application configuration in a centralized, dynamic manner. They provide features like key-value storage, versioning, and integration with various Azure/AWS services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>