<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Deployment Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/deployment/</link><description>Recent content in Deployment Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/deployment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Shadow Deployment</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/shadow_deployment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/shadow_deployment/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Shadow Deployment is a technique to test changes in a live production environment without impacting real users. It involves duplicating real production traffic to a new, &amp;ldquo;shadow&amp;rdquo; version of the application. This allows for observing the new system&amp;rsquo;s behavior under realistic load, identifying potential issues like performance bottlenecks, errors, or unexpected side effects, before a full rollout. The shadow system doesn’t serve responses to users; it purely receives and processes requests for monitoring purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern mitigates risks associated with deploying untested code and is a crucial component of robust continuous delivery pipelines. It allows teams to gain confidence in new features, bug fixes, or infrastructure changes under production conditions. Post-deployment analysis of shadow traffic can also yield valuable insights into user behavior and system interactions, informing further optimizations and refinements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Feature Validation:&lt;/strong&gt; Testing the functionality and performance of a new feature with live traffic without exposing it to end-users. This is vital for complex features that are difficult to test comprehensively in staging environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Evaluating the performance characteristics of a new application version under actual load conditions, detecting regressions or performance improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Schema Migrations:&lt;/strong&gt; Verifying the impact of database schema changes by running them against a shadow database populated with mirrored production data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrastructure Changes:&lt;/strong&gt; Validating changes to infrastructure components like caching layers, message queues, or load balancers without user disruption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canary Release Preparation:&lt;/strong&gt; As a precursor to canary releases, shadow deployment provides a first line of defense, identifying critical issues before even a small subset of users are exposed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix extensively uses shadow deployment, particularly for components of their recommendation engine and billing system. They mirror production traffic to shadow instances to evaluate new ranking algorithms or billing logic without affecting user experience. Any discrepancies are flagged and investigated before a full rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn:&lt;/strong&gt; LinkedIn employs shadow deployment to test changes to their core serving infrastructure. By shadowing production requests against new code paths, they can assess the impact on latency, throughput, and error rates before serving the changes to real users. This allows them to maintain a high level of service reliability during frequent deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istio (Service Mesh):&lt;/strong&gt; Istio, a popular service mesh, offers built-in support for traffic shadowing. You can configure it to mirror a percentage of traffic to a shadow version of a service, enabling testing and validation in a production setting. Traffic mirroring rules can be precisely controlled using Istio&amp;rsquo;s configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Canary Release</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/canary_release/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/canary_release/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Canary Release pattern is a deployment strategy where a new version of software is rolled out to a small subset of users or servers before being made available to the entire infrastructure. This allows for real-world testing of the new version with minimal impact, enabling teams to detect and address any unforeseen issues, performance regressions, or bugs in a controlled manner. The &amp;ldquo;canary&amp;rdquo; acts as an early warning system, hence the name, alerting the team to potential problems before a wider deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern prioritizes risk reduction and user experience. By observing the canary in production, teams can validate key metrics, gather user feedback, and ensure the stability of the new release. If the canary performs as expected, the rollout can proceed to more users; if issues arise, the new version can be quickly rolled back, preventing a widespread outage or negative impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architecture:&lt;/strong&gt; Canary releases are exceptionally well-suited for microservices. New versions of individual services can be deployed to a small number of instances behind a load balancer, allowing for targeted testing and minimal disruption to other services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-Traffic Websites &amp;amp; Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Rolling out updates to a small percentage of users during peak hours allows for observation of performance under realistic load without affecting the majority of the user base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex System Updates:&lt;/strong&gt; When updates involve significant changes to core functionality or dependencies, a canary release provides a safety net to ensure compatibility and stability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A/B Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Can be used in conjunction with A/B testing. A new version can be the &amp;ldquo;B&amp;rdquo; variant tested against a current version (&amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo;) allowing business metrics to drive the percentage rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gmail:&lt;/strong&gt; Gmail frequently employs canary releases to test new features. A small percentage of Gmail users (often Google employees) may see a new interface or functionality before it&amp;rsquo;s released to the general public. Monitoring these &amp;ldquo;canary&amp;rdquo; users’ behavior and reporting any issues helps refine the feature before a broad rollout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS CodeDeploy:&lt;/strong&gt; AWS CodeDeploy supports canary deployments for applications running on EC2, ECS, and other AWS services. It allows configuring incremental deployment strategies, automatically shifting traffic to the new version while monitoring its health. If problems are detected, CodeDeploy can automatically halt the deployment or roll back to the previous version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker Swarm/Kubernetes:&lt;/strong&gt; Container orchestration platforms like Docker Swarm and Kubernetes have built-in support for rolling updates and, by extension, canary deployments. You can specify the number of replicas for a new version and gradually increase them while monitoring performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LaunchDarkly:&lt;/strong&gt; As a Feature Management platform, LaunchDarkly specifically facilitates canary releases (and many other deployment strategies) by allowing development teams to release features to specific users or percentage of traffic, monitor performance, and rollback instantly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rolling Deployment</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/rolling_deployment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/rolling_deployment/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Rolling deployment is a software deployment strategy where new versions of an application are released to a subset of users or servers at a time, rather than all at once. This approach minimizes downtime and reduces the risk of widespread issues by allowing for gradual rollout and monitoring. If problems are detected, the deployment can be paused or rolled back, affecting only a small portion of the user base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core idea is to incrementally replace older instances with newer ones while maintaining application availability. This contrasts with strategies like blue/green deployments, which involve completely switching traffic. Rolling deployments often utilize load balancers and health checks to ensure only healthy instances serve traffic during the transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rolling deployments are widely used in modern software delivery pipelines for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Delivery/Continuous Integration (CI/CD):&lt;/strong&gt; They seamlessly integrate into automated CI/CD processes, enabling frequent and reliable releases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architecture:&lt;/strong&gt; Ideal for updating individual microservices without disrupting the entire application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Availability:&lt;/strong&gt; Minimizes downtime, essential for critical applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Mitigation:&lt;/strong&gt; Limits the blast radius of potential bugs or compatibility issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A/B Testing and Canary Releases:&lt;/strong&gt; Can be adapted for A/B testing by routing specific users or traffic to the new version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes:&lt;/strong&gt; Kubernetes natively supports rolling updates for deployments. The &lt;code&gt;kubectl apply&lt;/code&gt; command, combined with deployment configurations, handles the gradual replacement of pods, ensuring a specific number of pods are always available. Kubernetes also provides health checks and rollback capabilities integral to the rolling deployment process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS Elastic Beanstalk:&lt;/strong&gt; AWS Elastic Beanstalk provides a rolling update feature that simplifies deploying new versions of applications running on EC2 instances or containers. It manages capacity provisioning and health checks, automatically updating instances in batches and pausing if issues are detected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spinnaker:&lt;/strong&gt; This open-source, multi-cloud continuous delivery platform explicitly supports various deployment strategies, including rolling deployments (often called &amp;ldquo;canary&amp;rdquo;). Spinnaker provides advanced features like automated analysis of deployment metrics and intelligent rollback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Blue-Green Deployment</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/blue-green_deployment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/blue-green_deployment/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Blue-Green Deployment is a release strategy that reduces downtime and risk by running two identical environments, &amp;lsquo;blue&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;green&amp;rsquo;. The &amp;lsquo;blue&amp;rsquo; environment serves all production traffic, while the &amp;lsquo;green&amp;rsquo; environment is kept as a staging area for new releases. Once the new version is deployed and tested in the &amp;lsquo;green&amp;rsquo; environment to ensure it&amp;rsquo;s working correctly, traffic is switched from &amp;lsquo;blue&amp;rsquo; to &amp;lsquo;green&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach allows for instant rollbacks. If issues arise in the &amp;lsquo;green&amp;rsquo; environment after the switch, directing traffic back to the &amp;lsquo;blue&amp;rsquo; environment is a simple configuration change, minimizing downtime. It&amp;rsquo;s beneficial for achieving continuous delivery and mitigating the impact of potentially faulty deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue-Green Deployment is commonly applied in scenarios demanding high availability and minimal downtime, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring a seamless user experience during updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; Facilitating independent deployments of individual services without disrupting overall system functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Schema Changes:&lt;/strong&gt; Allowing schema updates to be tested thoroughly before going live, with a quick rollback option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical Business Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Where any downtime directly translates to financial losses or reputational damage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS Elastic Beanstalk:&lt;/strong&gt; Supports Blue/Green deployments directly, managing the creation and switching of environments for you. You deploy a new version to the &amp;ldquo;green&amp;rdquo; environment, test it against a load-balanced test version, and then promote the &amp;ldquo;green&amp;rdquo; environment to production, seamlessly swapping traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Kubernetes Engine (GKE):&lt;/strong&gt; Utilizes Kubernetes deployments and services to orchestrate Blue-Green deployments. You can deploy a new version as a separate deployment and then gradually shift traffic using service updates or ingress controllers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azure App Service:&lt;/strong&gt; Offers swap deployment slots, effectively implementing a Blue-Green strategy. You deploy the new version to a staging slot (&amp;ldquo;green&amp;rdquo;), warm it up, and then swap it with the production slot (&amp;ldquo;blue&amp;rdquo;). The old production slot remains as a rollback option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>