<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Microservices on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/microservices/</link><description>Recent content in Microservices on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:34:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/microservices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rate Limiting</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/rate_limiting/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 16:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/rate_limiting/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Rate limiting is a technique used to control the rate at which users or systems can access a resource. This is crucial for preventing abuse, ensuring service availability, and protecting backend systems from overload. By limiting the number of requests within a specific timeframe, rate limiting helps to maintain a stable and reliable system, especially under high load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pattern typically involves tracking requests from a specific source (e.g., IP address, user ID, API key) and enforcing a defined limit. When the limit is exceeded, the system responds with an error, such as a 429 &amp;ldquo;Too Many Requests&amp;rdquo; HTTP status code, or may temporarily block the offending source. Effective rate limiting requires careful consideration of the appropriate limits, tracking mechanisms, and error handling strategies based on the specific needs of the application and anticipated usage patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rate limiting is commonly used in a variety of scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public APIs:&lt;/strong&gt; Protecting APIs from excessive calls by malicious actors or poorly written clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Scraping Prevention:&lt;/strong&gt; Discouraging automated scraping of websites by limiting the number of requests from a single IP address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brute-Force Attack Mitigation:&lt;/strong&gt; Preventing attackers from repeatedly trying to guess passwords by limiting login attempts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource Protection:&lt;/strong&gt; Safeguarding expensive or limited resources, such as database queries or third-party service calls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architecture:&lt;/strong&gt; Controlling the flow of requests between microservices to prevent cascading failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Account Protection:&lt;/strong&gt; Limiting actions like password resets or email sending to prevent abuse of user accounts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter API:&lt;/strong&gt; Twitter employs rate limiting extensively for its API. Different API endpoints have different rate limits, which are documented for developers. These limits are based on factors like authentication type (application-only vs. user-context) and endpoint usage. The API returns specific rate limit headers with each response, informing developers how many requests they have remaining and when the limits will reset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub API:&lt;/strong&gt; Similar to Twitter, GitHub also uses rate limiting to protect its API. GitHub&amp;rsquo;s rate limits are based on authenticated vs. unauthenticated requests, with authenticated requests receiving significantly higher limits. They provide detailed documentation on their rate limits and how to handle 403 errors (which indicate rate limiting) using the &lt;code&gt;X-RateLimit-Remaining&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;X-RateLimit-Reset&lt;/code&gt; headers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redis RateLimiter:&lt;/strong&gt; The Redis RateLimiter library (available in multiple languages) provides a flexible and scalable way to implement rate limiting using Redis as a storage backend. It allows defining rate limits based on various keys (e.g., user ID, IP address) and uses Redis&amp;rsquo;s atomic operations to ensure accurate request counting and limit enforcement. This is often used in microservices architectures where a centralized rate limiting service is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Database per Service</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/database_per_service/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/database_per_service/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Database per Service pattern dictates that each microservice should have its own dedicated database. This contrasts with a shared database approach where multiple services access a single database, which is a common anti-pattern in microservice architectures. The key principle is to decouple data storage from the services themselves, allowing each service full control over its data model and technology choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern enhances a microservice&amp;rsquo;s autonomy, resilience, and scalability. Independent databases allow services to evolve without impacting others, support different database technologies best suited for their specific needs, and minimize contention. While it introduces operational complexity, this complexity is often outweighed by the benefits of loose coupling and increased agility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Database per Service pattern is commonly used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservice Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the primary use case, where independent services require independent data management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Domain-Driven Design (DDD):&lt;/strong&gt; When applying DDD, each bounded context naturally aligns with a dedicated database ensuring data consistency within the context but allowing flexible data representation across different contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large-Scale Web Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Breaking down monolithic databases into smaller, service-specific databases simplifies scaling, maintenance, and independent deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-Native Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; The pattern fits well with cloud-based database services that facilitate scaling and management of multiple instances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix famously utilizes this pattern. Different functional areas such as user accounts, recommendations, streaming data, and billing, each operate with their own database tailored to their precise requirements. For instance, the recommendation service might employ a graph database for efficient relationship analysis, while the user account service uses a relational database for structured user data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon:&lt;/strong&gt; Amazon&amp;rsquo;s e-commerce platform is built on a microservices architecture, and each service (e.g., product catalog, shopping cart, order processing) has its own database. This allows Amazon to scale individual services independently based on demand. Their use of different database technologies (relational, NoSQL, etc.) is also enabled by this pattern, optimised to each service’s workload.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spotify:&lt;/strong&gt; Spotify leverages database per service in their backend. Different microservices like user profiles, music catalog, playlists, and payments each have their own dedicated databases. This separation allows Spotify to update and scale different parts of its application without affecting others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Config Server</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/config_server/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 14:37:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/config_server/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Config Server pattern centralizes configuration management for distributed systems, particularly microservices. Instead of embedding configuration directly within applications or duplicating it across various deployment environments, a dedicated Config Server acts as a single source of truth. Client applications retrieve their configurations from the server dynamically, allowing changes to be propagated without requiring application restarts or redeployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern greatly simplifies configuration management, improves consistency, and enables dynamic updates in response to changing conditions. It supports differing configurations for different environments (development, staging, production) and application instances, bolstering agility and reducing operational overhead. The Config Server often integrates with version control systems for auditability and rollback capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Config Server pattern is widely used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; As configurations are often environment-specific and need to be updated frequently, a config server is essential for managing disparate service settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-Native Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Dynamic environments and autoscaling necessitate the ability to adjust configurations on the fly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Integration/Continuous Delivery (CI/CD) Pipelines:&lt;/strong&gt; Allows settings to be updated as part of automated deployments without altering the application code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large-Scale Distributed Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Simplifies control and auditability of application settings across a complex infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring Cloud Config:&lt;/strong&gt; A popular Java-based framework that provides a Config Server implementation coupled with Spring Cloud’s service discovery capabilities. It supports various backends like Git, Vault, and a database, enabling flexible configuration storage and versioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azure App Configuration:&lt;/strong&gt; Microsoft Azure&amp;rsquo;s fully managed configuration service. It provides dynamic configuration updates, feature flags, and secret management, integrating seamlessly with other Azure services. Features include versioning, labels, and access control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consul (HashiCorp):&lt;/strong&gt; While also a service discovery tool, Consul includes a key-value store that effectively functions as a distributed configuration server. Applications can subscribe to configuration updates and receive notifications when changes occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ambassador</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/ambassador/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/ambassador/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Ambassador pattern provides a single point of entry for a system (or set of backend services) while abstracting away the internal complexity. It acts as a forward-facing proxy that handles requests, potentially transforming them, adding security, and routing them to the appropriate backend. This decouples clients from the backend implementation details, allowing for independent evolution and scaling of both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ambassador pattern is frequently used in microservice architectures to manage external access to internal services. It’s beneficial when you need to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shield Backend Complexity:&lt;/strong&gt; Hide the internal structure and endpoints of services from external clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement Cross-Cutting Concerns:&lt;/strong&gt; Add features like authentication, authorization, rate limiting, and monitoring without modifying the backend services themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facilitate Versioning:&lt;/strong&gt; Manage different versions of backend services and handle request routing based on versioning schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplify Client Interaction:&lt;/strong&gt; Provide a consistent and simplified interface for clients, even as the backend evolves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enable Protocol Translation:&lt;/strong&gt; Expose services via one protocol (e.g., REST) while backend services use a different protocol (e.g., gRPC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kong API Gateway:&lt;/strong&gt; Kong is a widely used open-source API gateway often deployed as an “Ambassador” in front of microservices. It provides features like authentication, rate limiting, transformation, and observability. Clients interact with Kong, and Kong forwards requests to the appropriate backend service based on configured routes and plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS API Gateway:&lt;/strong&gt; Amazon&amp;rsquo;s API Gateway is a fully managed service that acts as a front door for applications to access data, business logic, or functionality from your backend services. Similar to Kong, it handles request routing, authentication, authorization, and other critical functions, shielding the backend from direct client access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istio Ingress Gateway:&lt;/strong&gt; In a service mesh like Istio, the Ingress Gateway functions as an Ambassador. It handles incoming traffic from outside the mesh, enforcing policies and routing requests to services within the mesh. This allows for consistent management of external access points across a fleet of microservices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bulkhead Cache</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/bulkhead_cache/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/bulkhead_cache/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Bulkhead Cache pattern enhances system resilience by isolating a shared, potentially unreliable resource – a cache – from the rest of the application. It achieves this by limiting the number of concurrent requests that can access the cache. If the cache is slow or fails, the bulkhead prevents cascading failures by allowing a managed fallback, typically to a slower, more reliable data source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is particularly useful in microservice architectures where multiple services rely on a common caching layer. It protects downstream services from being overwhelmed by cache issues. It’s also applicable in monolithic applications facing high load or dealing with third-party cache providers that have performance SLAs. Specifically helpful when caching dependencies have unpredictable latency or availability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix Hystrix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix&amp;rsquo;s Hystrix library pioneered the bulkhead pattern, and included specific support for caching. Hystrix would wrap cache access with a thread pool or semaphore to limit concurrency, and provided mechanisms to fall back to data sources when the cache was unavailable or response times exceeded a threshold. It is a common implementation in Java microservices for rate limiting and failure isolation of cache access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redis with Lettuce/Jedis:&lt;/strong&gt; When using Redis as a cache in Java applications, libraries like Lettuce or Jedis can be configured with connection pools. While primarily for connection management, limiting the pool size effectively creates a bulkhead. If Redis becomes unresponsive, it prevents the application from exhausting all connections, allowing a controlled fallback and preventing total application outage. Specifically, you can configure maximum pooled connections to bound resource usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Distributed Tracing</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/distributed_tracing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/distributed_tracing/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Distributed tracing is a methodology used to profile and monitor transactions as they flow through a distributed system. Unlike traditional logging and monitoring, which focus on individual service metrics, distributed tracing tracks requests across multiple services, providing insight into the entire end-to-end transaction path. This is crucial for identifying performance bottlenecks, understanding dependencies, and diagnosing errors in complex microservices architectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each request is assigned a unique Trace ID, and each distinct operation within a service involved in that request is assigned a Span ID. These IDs are propagated through the system, allowing tracing systems to correlate logs and metrics from different services, constructing a complete picture of the transaction’s lifecycle. The goal is visibility into how a request travels, which services handle it, and how long each step takes, enabling optimization and quicker resolution of issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed tracing is commonly used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices:&lt;/strong&gt; Essential for debugging and optimizing interactions between multiple independent services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud-Native Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Provides vital observability in dynamic, scaled-out environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex Business Transactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Helps understand the flow and performance of multi-step operations like order processing or user registration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance Monitoring:&lt;/strong&gt; Identifies slow services and dependencies in real-time, allowing for proactive scaling or optimization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Root Cause Analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; Pinpoints the exact service and operation causing an error, reducing mean time to resolution (MTTR).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jaeger (Uber):&lt;/strong&gt; Originally built by Uber to monitor their massive distributed systems, Jaeger is an open-source, end-to-end distributed tracing system. It allows developers to collect traces and view them in a graphical user interface, identifying performance issues and dependencies. Jaeger supports various tracing protocols like OpenTracing and OpenTelemetry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zipkin (Twitter):&lt;/strong&gt; Another popular open-source distributed tracing system, Zipkin was initially developed by Twitter. It provides similar functionality to Jaeger, allowing you to trace requests through your services. Zipkin’s web UI enables visualization of trace data, making it easier to identify bottlenecks and errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS X-Ray:&lt;/strong&gt; A fully managed distributed tracing service provided by Amazon Web Services. It automatically traces requests as they travel through AWS services (like Lambda, EC2, DynamoDB) and allows you to visualize the performance of your applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Trace:&lt;/strong&gt; A similar fully managed service offered by Google Cloud Platform, providing detailed trace information for applications running on GCP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OpenTelemetry:&lt;/strong&gt; While not a tracing system &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, OpenTelemetry is a vendor-neutral observability framework and a collection of APIs, SDKs, and tools for generating and collecting telemetry data (traces, metrics, and logs). It’s becoming the standard for instrumenting applications for observability and supports exporting trace data to various backends like Jaeger, Zipkin, and cloud provider tracing services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>API Gateway</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/api_gateway/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/api_gateway/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The API Gateway pattern provides a single entry point for all clients accessing a set of backend services. It sits in front of these services, abstracting their complexity and providing features like request routing, composition, transformation, and authentication. This simplifies client development, improves security, and enables easier evolution of the backend services without impacting clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the API Gateway decouples the client from the internal microservice architecture. It handles tasks like protocol translation (e.g., REST to gRPC), data aggregation from multiple services, and rate limiting. It&amp;rsquo;s a central point of control for API management and can also offload concerns like SSL termination and caching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The API Gateway pattern is commonly used in the following scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s essential for managing external access to a distributed system of microservices, shielding clients from the intricacies of service discovery and internal communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile Backends:&lt;/strong&gt; Mobile apps often benefit from reduced network requests and tailored data formats provided by an API Gateway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Applications with Multiple Backends:&lt;/strong&gt; When a web application relies on various backend systems (legacy systems, third-party APIs, modern microservices), an API Gateway can consolidate access and simplify integration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolving Backends:&lt;/strong&gt; Allows changes to backend services without requiring updates to clients. The gateway handles the transformation and routing changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security and Monitoring:&lt;/strong&gt; Provides a central point to enforce security policies (authentication, authorization) and monitor API usage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix&amp;rsquo;s architecture extensively utilizes API Gateways (Zuul, now replaced by newer solutions) to handle over 3 billion device requests per day. The gateway routes requests to different underlying microservices responsible for various features like user authentication, recommendation engines, and video streaming. It abstracts the complexities of the backend, enabling better scalability and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS API Gateway:&lt;/strong&gt; Amazon Web Services provides a fully managed API Gateway service. Developers can create, publish, maintain, monitor, and secure APIs at any scale. It integrates seamlessly with other AWS services like Lambda, EC2, and DynamoDB, allowing for the creation of serverless backends and hybrid architectures. Features include request validation, transformation, authorization, and caching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kong:&lt;/strong&gt; Kong is a popular open-source API gateway built on Nginx. It&amp;rsquo;s often used in cloud-native and microservices environments due to its extensibility via plugins for features like authentication, traffic control, and analytics. Kong provides a declarative configuration and supports a wide range of protocols and authentication methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>