<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Robustness Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/robustness/</link><description>Recent content in Robustness Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://swpatterns.com/pattern_types/robustness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fail Fast</title><link>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/fail_fast/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://swpatterns.com/pattern/fail_fast/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Fail Fast pattern is a strategy for dealing with errors as quickly as possible. Instead of attempting to continue execution after detecting a problem, the system immediately halts and reports the error. This minimizes the potential for cascading failures, reduces debugging time, and makes error handling more explicit. By failing fast, developers can identify and address issues early in the process, leading to more robust and reliable software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fail Fast is commonly used in scenarios where input validation is critical, such as parsing data, processing user requests, or interacting with external systems. It’s also applied during development and testing to pinpoint bugs rapidly. Areas where it finds frequent application include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;API Gateways:&lt;/strong&gt; Rejecting invalid requests before they reach backend services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Pipelines:&lt;/strong&gt; Stopping processing when encountering malformed data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unit Tests:&lt;/strong&gt; Asserting conditions early to avoid misleading results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuration Loading:&lt;/strong&gt; Failing immediately if required configuration options are missing or invalid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; statement:&lt;/strong&gt; Python’s &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; statement is a built-in mechanism to ensure that certain conditions are met during program execution. If the condition is false, an &lt;code&gt;AssertionError&lt;/code&gt; is raised immediately, halting the program. This is a quintessential Fail Fast implementation for internal consistency checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;python
def process_data(data):
assert isinstance(data, list), &amp;ldquo;Data must be a list&amp;rdquo;
assert len(data) &amp;gt; 0, &amp;ldquo;Data list cannot be empty&amp;rdquo;
# Continue processing if assertions pass
return sum(data)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruby on Rails Validations:&lt;/strong&gt; Ruby on Rails utilizes a validation framework that employs the Fail Fast principle. When a model is validated, it checks each validation rule sequentially. If a rule fails, errors are added to the model, and the validation process stops – subsequent rules are not checked. This prevents unnecessary processing and ensures the user is presented with all relevant errors at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ruby
class User &amp;lt; ApplicationRecord
validates :name, presence: true, length: { maximum: 50 }
validates :email, presence: true, uniqueness: true
end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;user = User.new(email: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="mailto:existing_email@example.com"&gt;existing_email@example.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, name: &amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo;)
if user.valid?
puts &amp;ldquo;User is valid&amp;rdquo;
else
puts &amp;ldquo;User is invalid&amp;rdquo; #Validation stops after name presence check fails
puts user.errors.full_messages # Shows only the &amp;lsquo;Name cannot be blank&amp;rsquo; error
end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>