<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>UI Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/ui/</link><description>Recent content in UI Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/ui/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Component-based UI</title><link>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/component-based_ui/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/component-based_ui/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Component-based UI is an architectural pattern that structures a user interface as a composition of independent, reusable components. Each component encapsulates its own logic, rendering, and data, and interacts with other components through well-defined interfaces. This approach promotes modularity, maintainability, and testability, allowing developers to build complex UIs from smaller, manageable pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core idea is to break down the UI into isolated, self-contained units. These components can be combined, nested, and reused across different parts of the application, reducing code duplication and improving consistency. Changes to one component ideally have minimal impact on others, simplifying development and debugging. This pattern is fundamental to modern front-end development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Component-based UI is ubiquitous in modern web and mobile development. It&amp;rsquo;s used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large-scale web applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Where maintainability and scalability are crucial. Frameworks like React, Angular, and Vue.js are built around this pattern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design systems:&lt;/strong&gt; To create a library of reusable UI elements that enforce brand consistency and streamline development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile app development:&lt;/strong&gt; React Native, Flutter, and SwiftUI all leverage component-based architectures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Game development:&lt;/strong&gt; UI elements in games are often built as components for flexibility and performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desktop application development:&lt;/strong&gt; Frameworks like Electron and others allow for component-based UI construction in desktop apps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;React:&lt;/strong&gt; React is a JavaScript library specifically designed for building user interfaces using a component-based approach. Developers define UI elements as reusable React components, which manage their own state and rendering logic. Components can be composed to create more complex UIs. For example, a &lt;code&gt;Button&lt;/code&gt; component, a &lt;code&gt;TextField&lt;/code&gt; component, and a &lt;code&gt;Label&lt;/code&gt; component can be combined to create a &lt;code&gt;FormInput&lt;/code&gt; component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Angular:&lt;/strong&gt; Angular is a comprehensive framework for building client applications. It heavily utilizes components as the building blocks of the UI. Angular components consist of a template (HTML), a class (TypeScript) that defines the component&amp;rsquo;s logic, and metadata that configures the component. Angular&amp;rsquo;s dependency injection system further enhances component reusability and testability. A &lt;code&gt;ProductCard&lt;/code&gt; component might encapsulate the display of a single product, including its image, name, and price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storybook:&lt;/strong&gt; Storybook is an open-source tool for developing UI components in isolation. It allows developers to create and showcase individual components with various states and interactions, making it easier to test and document them. It&amp;rsquo;s used with React, Angular, Vue, and other frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Presentation Model</title><link>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/presentation_model/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/presentation_model/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Presentation Model pattern dictates a clear separation between the data and business logic of an application, and the UI layer responsible for displaying it. The Presentation Model acts as an intermediary, exposing data specifically tailored for the View. It abstracts the complexities of the underlying data and business rules, handling formatting, filtering and state management for the UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern promotes testability and maintainability by decoupling the UI from the core application logic. Changes to the UI or the underlying business logic don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily impact each other, as long as the Presentation Model&amp;rsquo;s interface remains stable. It&amp;rsquo;s particularly useful in scenarios where complex UI interactions are required, or when supporting multiple views from the same data source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Presentation Model is frequently employed in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model-View-ViewModel (MVVM) architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; The Presentation Model serves as the ‘VM’ part, providing data bindings and command implementations for the View.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rich Internet Applications (RIAs):&lt;/strong&gt; For complex UIs built with technologies like JavaScript frameworks (React, Angular, Vue.js) where the UI requires a prepared and formatted dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desktop Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; In frameworks like WPF and Swing, where complex data presentation and user interaction handling are commonplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications needing separation of concerns:&lt;/strong&gt; Any application where you want to isolate the presentation logic from the business logic for easier testing and modification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WPF (Windows Presentation Foundation):&lt;/strong&gt; WPF heavily utilizes the Presentation Model pattern (often alongside MVVM). A WPF application displaying a list of customers would have a &lt;code&gt;CustomerView&lt;/code&gt; (the UI), a &lt;code&gt;CustomerPresentationModel&lt;/code&gt; that formats customer data for display (e.g., formatting phone numbers, displaying addresses), and &lt;code&gt;CustomerBusinessLogic&lt;/code&gt; that handles the creation, retrieval, and modification of customer data. The &lt;code&gt;CustomerPresentationModel&lt;/code&gt; exposes properties like &lt;code&gt;CustomerName&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;FormattedAddress&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;PhoneNumber&lt;/code&gt; that the &lt;code&gt;CustomerView&lt;/code&gt; binds to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;React with Redux:&lt;/strong&gt; Although often associated with Flux or MVVM-ish patterns, React components can be seen as ‘Views’ that consume data from a ‘Presentation Model’ orchestrated by Redux. Redux selectors act as presentation models, transforming the application state (the ‘Data’) into props specifically designed for the React components. For example, a selector might take a raw user object from the store and create a &lt;code&gt;userProfile&lt;/code&gt; object containing only the name, email, and profile picture appropriate for display in a user profile component. The presentation logic lives in the selectors, keeping the React components purely presentational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>