<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cloud Patterns on SWPatterns.com</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/cloud/</link><description>Recent content in Cloud Patterns on SWPatterns.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern_types/cloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Immutable Infrastructure</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/immutable_infrastructure/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/immutable_infrastructure/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Immutable infrastructure is a practice where servers are never modified after they’re provisioned. Instead, if a change is required, a new server is provisioned with the updated configuration, and the old server is replaced. This approach treats infrastructure as code, emphasizing version control and repeatability. It drastically reduces configuration drift, simplifies updates and rollbacks, increases security by minimizing the attack surface, and improves overall system reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern contrasts with traditional infrastructure management, where servers are often updated in place. Immutable infrastructure promotes a &amp;ldquo;replace, don&amp;rsquo;t repair&amp;rdquo; philosophy, meaning that any intervention on a server beyond its initial provisioning is avoided. This leads to more predictable and consistent environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immutable Infrastructure is commonly used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Environments:&lt;/strong&gt; Ideal for platforms like AWS, Azure, and Google Cloud where infrastructure can be rapidly provisioned and deprovisioned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Delivery Pipelines:&lt;/strong&gt; Integrates seamlessly with CI/CD pipelines, enabling automated and reliable deployments of updated infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microservices Architectures:&lt;/strong&gt; Supports the frequent updates and scaling requirements of independent microservices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disaster Recovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Simplifies recovery by allowing for quick and consistent recreation of infrastructure from images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security Hardening:&lt;/strong&gt; Reduces the window of vulnerability by minimizing the need for patching existing servers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker:&lt;/strong&gt; Docker containers are a prime example of immutable infrastructure. Once a container image is built, it&amp;rsquo;s not modified. To update an application, a new image is built and deployed, replacing the old container. Docker Hub and other container registries serve as the image stores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS Machine Images (AMIs) / Azure Managed Images / Google Compute Images:&lt;/strong&gt; Cloud providers offer mechanisms to create and store immutable images of virtual machine configurations. These images can be used to launch new instances, ensuring consistency across deployments. Terraform or CloudFormation can then be used to codify the image creation and instance launch processes, solidifying the immutability and repeatability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Packer:&lt;/strong&gt; HashiCorp Packer automates the creation of machine images for various platforms (AWS, Azure, Google Cloud, VMware, etc.). Packer outputs identical machine images every time, even if the underlying infrastructure changes, promoting immutability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes:&lt;/strong&gt; Kubernetes utilizes immutable containers and declarative configuration to manage application deployments. Updates are performed by rolling out new container versions, rather than modifying existing ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Init Container</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/init_container/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/init_container/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;The Init Container pattern addresses the challenge of application dependencies and setup requirements in container orchestration systems like Kubernetes. It defines a specialized container that runs &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the application containers within a Pod. Init Containers are crucial for ensuring that shared resources are available, configurations are applied, and necessary pre-conditions are met before the main application containers start, preventing application failures due to uninitialized dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern enhances Pod robustness and simplifies deployment. By offloading initialization tasks to a dedicated container, the application containers remain focused on their core function. Init Containers can handle tasks with different requirements (e.g., different base images, network access) than the primary application containers, providing flexibility and isolation. Furthermore, Init Containers ensure a predictable startup order within a Pod, critical for maintaining system consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Migrations:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring database schemas are up to date before an application connects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuration File Generation:&lt;/strong&gt; Dynamically generating configuration files based on environment variables or secrets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Readiness:&lt;/strong&gt; Waiting for network services to become available before starting dependent applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downloading Dependencies:&lt;/strong&gt; Fetching necessary binaries, libraries or data before application startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting Permissions:&lt;/strong&gt; Adjusting file or directory permissions required by the application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Installing Certificates:&lt;/strong&gt; Installing required SSL/TLS certificates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes Deployments:&lt;/strong&gt; Kubernetes natively supports Init Containers. A common use case is to use an Init Container to fetch secrets from a vault (like HashiCorp Vault) and write them to a shared volume that the application containers can access. This ensures secure access to credentials without hardcoding them in the application image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helm Charts:&lt;/strong&gt; Helm charts often incorporate Init Containers to handle application-specific setup tasks. For example, a chart deploying a Redis cluster might use an Init Container to bootstrap the cluster with initial configuration, establishing a consistent state before the main Redis containers join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Space-Based Architecture</title><link>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/space-based_architecture/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.swpatterns.com/pattern/space-based_architecture/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;Space-Based Architecture is a distributed architectural pattern where application functionality is broken down into independently deployable services, often referred to as &amp;ldquo;spaces.&amp;rdquo; These spaces are designed to be loosely coupled, communicating primarily through well-defined APIs and asynchronous messaging. Each space owns its data and can be scaled and updated independently, promoting agility and resilience. This contrasts with monolithic architectures or tightly coupled service-oriented architectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern is particularly useful for large, complex applications that require high scalability, fault tolerance, and rapid development cycles. It&amp;rsquo;s well-suited for microservices implementations, event-driven systems, and applications that need to adapt quickly to changing business requirements. The independent nature of spaces allows teams to work autonomously and deploy updates without impacting other parts of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space-Based Architecture is commonly used in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E-commerce Platforms:&lt;/strong&gt; Separating product catalog, shopping cart, order processing, and payment services into independent spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Media Networks:&lt;/strong&gt; Isolating features like user profiles, news feeds, messaging, and search into distinct spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Trading Systems:&lt;/strong&gt; Decoupling order management, risk assessment, and execution services for improved performance and reliability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IoT Platforms:&lt;/strong&gt; Handling data ingestion, device management, and analytics as separate, scalable spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netflix:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix heavily utilizes a space-based architecture. Different aspects of the streaming service, such as user authentication, recommendation engines, video encoding, and content delivery, are all implemented as independent microservices (spaces). This allows Netflix to scale individual components based on demand and deploy updates without disrupting the entire platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Web Services (AWS):&lt;/strong&gt; AWS itself is a prime example. Each AWS service (e.g., S3, EC2, Lambda) operates as a largely independent space with its own API, data storage, and scaling mechanisms. The services interact through defined interfaces and event-driven communication, enabling a highly scalable and resilient cloud platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spotify:&lt;/strong&gt; Spotify&amp;rsquo;s backend is built on a space-based architecture, dividing functionality into areas like music catalog, user accounts, playlist management, and recommendation algorithms. This allows for independent scaling and development of each feature, supporting millions of users and a vast music library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>